Well, it's 1850, y'all. And that means
rival factions in the North and the
South are losing their ever loving minds
about whether slavery should be extended
into the West. So, I don't know about
you, but I'm kind of in the mood for a
compromise that's going to fix all that
bickering. That's right. It's time for
the compromise of 1850. And while it was
certainly a compromise, it really didn't
fix much. So, if you're ready to get
them brain cows milked, let's get to it.
Okay. Now, as I mentioned in the last
video, the effects of the
Mexican-American War were kind of a
mixed bag. I mean, yeah, there were
certainly tiny boxes of nerds in that
bag, which are always cause for great
rejoice. In that case, the Treaty of
Guadalupe Halago granted the United
States metric buttloadads of land in the
west. But there were also some big nasty
circus peanuts in that bag, which if I
remember right, are the only edible
substance available in Dante's Seventh
Circle of Hell. And of course, the
stalest peanut of all was the bitter
debate that erupted over the expansion
of slavery into the lands in the Mexican
session. But those ragy factions were
further divided by two additional
developments. As I mentioned in the last
video, in 1846, an anti-slavery
congressman introduced the Wilmont
proviso for a vote which proposed a
complete ban on slavery in any territory
gained from the Mexican-American War.
Now, the bill failed, but it still
enraged southern congressmen who saw it
as a plot to diminish their political
power over time. And then the second
development that revealed a deep
sectional rift was California's
application for statehood in 1849. And
that was a problem because those
rascally Californians went ahead and
applied to enter the union as a free
state, which of course would upset the
balance in the Senate between slave and
free states. And then the Oregon
territory was added in 1848 with a ban
on slavery as well. So all of a sudden,
every representative in Congress had a
mouthful of circus peanuts and it became
an emergency to try to find a solution.
And essentially the debate had four
distinct sides. But before I tell you
what those sides were, let me just
mention that if you need help getting an
A in your class and a five on your exam
in May, then you might want to check out
my A Push Heimler review guide. It's got
everything you need to study as fast as
possible and that link is in the
description. Okay, so we got a bunch of
land and now we're debating whether
slavery should be allowed to expand. So
here are the four different solutions
that various leaders proposed. First,
there should be no restriction on the
expansion of slavery. And the poster boy
for this argument was John C. Calhoun of
nullification crisis and slavery as a
positive good thing. Essentially, this
faction argued that slavery follows the
flag. In other words, to own enslaved
people is a constitutional right and any
attempt to hinder slave owners from
taking their property wherever they
liked was unconstitutional. And not
surprisingly, this position was
wholesale embraced by states in the deep
south. Okay. The second proposal was to
extend the provisions of the Missouri
Compromise throughout the new territory.
So remember from the last unit that the
Missouri Compromise had settled the
territorial slavery question by allowing
territories and states below Missouri
southern border to perpetuate and
maintain slavery. And then for those
states above the line, slavery was
banned. So tidy, so clean. butt, big
butt, massive butt. That line of
demarcation only extended through the
territory acquired in the Louisiana
purchase. So advocates of this position
proposed that the dividing line be
extended through the lands of the
Mexican session all the way to the
Pacific Ocean. And this position was
favored by many northern Democrats as
well as James Buchanan, Poke Secretary
of State. Okay. And then the third
proposal was to decide the slavery
question in the new territories by means
of popular sovereignty. And the
definition is in the word itself.
Popular means people and sovereignty
means power. In other words, this
proposal suggested that people who lived
in the territories could decide for
themselves whether to allow slavery.
Now, it was northern Democrat Lewis Cass
who first proposed this idea when
Congress was yelling at each other over
the Wilmont provisor. But later, this
concept got a new champion, namely
Democrat Steven Douglas. Now, in theory,
this seemed like a good option, right?
Like, by branding it popular
sovereignty, Cass and Douglas linked
this question to the Democratic ideals
of the country. Like, shouldn't
Americans be able to decide for
themselves whether or not to allow
slavery? But in practical terms, the
issue was a little more complicated.
Like neither man really explained how
this kind of voting would work, nor did
they comment on several difficult issues
that would arise as a result of this
policy. For example, if a territory was
already home to a population of
slaveholders and it voted to abolish
slavery, then what would happen to the
enslaved people and the planters who
claimed ownership over them? Regardless,
this position was favored by another
faction of northern Democrats. And then
the fourth attempt at a solution was to
restrict slavery to its current
boundaries. Now, this argument was made,
not surprisingly, by abolitionists whose
goal was to prevent the further spread
of slavery. Now, this position was put
forth and supported by a coalition of
Democrats and free soil leaders, which
was a group formed in 1848 in response
to the war and whose members had gained
several seats in Congress. And by their
reckoning, by forbidding the expansion
of what they called the slave power,
slavery would eventually die out, even
in the South, as their political
influence weakened without a chance to
control new territories and states. So,
I don't know about you, but to me, that
sounds like an unresolvable debate. I
mean, if only there was a senator from
Kentucky who could take all four of
those meaty factions and put them
together into a nice compromised
sandwich. Oh yeah, there is such a man.
That's right. You know him, you love
him. It's the great compromiser himself,
Henry Clay. So, don't forget that Clay
was the one who resolved this issue 30
years prior with the Missouri
Compromise, and by all measures, it was
a pretty decent sandwich. So, let's see
what he does here. So, the compromise of
1850 contained four major provisions.
First, California would be admitted as a
free state. Second, the rest of the land
gained from the Mexican session would be
divided into two territories, New Mexico
and Utah, and there the slavery question
would be decided by popular sovereignty.
Third, Washington DC would abolish the
slave trade, though slavery itself would
be allowed to remain. And fourth, a
stricter fugitive slave law would be
enacted. Now, as it turned out, none of
the groups involved were entirely happy
with the compromise, but it passed
anyway and made at least some progress
on calming down the sectional tensions
over slavery. However, apparently Clay
wasn't wearing his hairet when he made
that sandwich because there were two
thick nasty hairs in the mayo. And these
two parts, far from calming sectional
tension down, only increased it. So
nasty hair number one. The fact that
states formed out of the New Mexico and
Utah territory could decide the slavery
question by popular sovereignty deeply
upset supporters of slavery. You see,
for them, the Missouri Compromise was
nigh unescriptural in its promise that
slavery had a guaranteed path for
westward expansion so long as it
remained south of the 3630 line. Okay,
nasty hair. Number two, the fugitive
slave law deeply disturbed the
abolitionist north. In essence, this law
said that any American who encountered a
fugitive or, you know, runaway enslaved
person must work to get them arrested
and returned to their enslaver without
the provision of a jury trial. And
abolitionists felt that such a law
forced them to participate in the
perpetuation of an institution which
they hated and which in some cases felt
was morally repugnant. And so, as you
may or may not know, if you bite into a
sandwich with hairs in it, it really
doesn't matter how good the sandwich is.
All you're tasting is hairs. Okay, I'm
starting to gross my own self out with
that. Let's be done with that metaphor.
Anyway, briefly, let me show you at
least one way that resistance to the
compromise of 1850 led to its almost
complete failure to solve the slavery
problem in the west. And mainly, it was
the fugitive slave law at the heart of
the resistance. Some northern
abolitionists simply nullified the law
and continued to assist enslaved people
who escaped their bondage. And then some
states in the north passed personal
liberty laws which guaranteed every
person within its borders, including
runaway enslaved people, the right to a
jury trial. However, even that was still
a pretty complicated matter since under
the provisions of the fugitive slave
law, people accused of being runaways
were forbidden from giving their
testimony and arguing for their own
innocence. Additionally, federal
commissioners who oversaw these cases
were given $10 if they ruled that the
defendant was a runaway slave, but only
$5 if they ruled that he or she was
free. So, even state laws aimed at
resistance were met with serious
obstacles. And then the Wisconsin
Supreme Court handed down a decision
stating that the fugitive slave law was
unconstitutional since it violated the
rights of citizens not to participate in
slavery. Basically this decision
amounted to an act of judicial
nullification. However, that case then
came before the Supreme Court in Abelman
v Booth in 1859 and the court struck
down the decision of the Wisconsin court
reaffirming the supremacy of federal
decisions above state decisions. And in
this case, it meant that no state could
challenge the authority of the fugitive
slave law. And any person who refused to
help return escapees to their
enslavement would face fines or
imprisonment. So, hey, credit where
credit is due. Henry Clay took a big
swing and did his best to staunch the
gaping neck wound called the expansion
of slavery. But as it turned out, Clay
nor any other compromised-minded
American couldn't find nearly enough
gauze to stop that bleeding. And I will
pick up that juicy tail in the next
video. Okay, you can click here to watch
my other videos from unit 5, or you can
click here to grab my Himler review
guide, which is going to help you study
as fast as possible. I'm glad you came
around, and I'll catch you on the
flip-flop. I'm lar.